Register of the Ansis Pommers Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ansis Pommers papers
1929-2012
2007C6
Pommers, Ansis.
19 manuscript boxes (7.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Ansis Pommers Papers contain materials pertaining to the history of the Latvian emigration after World War II, from the experience of Latvians in Displaced Persons camps in Germany immediately after the war to their subsequent lives as immigrants in the United States, Canada and other countries. In particular, the collection has numerous publications that reflect the efforts of Latvian Americans to sustain their culture through various community based institutions and publications.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Use copies of all sound recordings in the collection are available for immediate access.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007, with subsequent increments
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1935 Born, Rīga, Latvia
1945-1949 Lives with family in the Displaced Persons camp in Fischbach, Germany
1950 Emigrates with family to the United States
1955 Awarded A.A. degree, Sierra Community College
1966 Awarded B.S. degree, Sacramento State College
1966-1992 Works as an engineer for Link Flight Simulation Systems
1970 Awarded M.S. degree, Santa Clara University
1992 Starts own technical writing business
2007 Publishes Fis̆bachas virs̆os 1945-1950
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ansis Pommers Papers contain materials pertaining to the history of the Latvian emigration after World War II, from the experience of Latvians in Displaced Persons camps in Germany immediately after the war to their subsequent lives as immigrants in the United States, Canada, and other countries. In particular, the collection has numerous publications that reflect the efforts of Latvian Americans to sustain their culture through various community based institutions and publications.
The two edited works by Pommers in the papers describe the lives of Latvians in the Displaced Persons camp in Fischbach, Germany, where Pommers and his family were among the camp residents. The first of these works, Fis̆bachas virs̆os 1945-1950, provides a comprehensive account of life in Fischbach, including the numerous cultural activities that took place in the camp. The work describes the educational institutions in the camp, and, in particular, the Kārlis Skalbe elementary school and high school. The second edited work, Lāpa 15, describes the final period of the Skalbe schools and includes many short biographies of the schools' graduates, with details on their later careers in the countries they emigrated to.
The Printed matter series in the collection contains many serial issues, most of them emanating from Latvian American organizations. These include numerous issues of the newsletter of the Northern California Latvian Association. There are also many issues of Jaunā Gaita, the most prominent Latvian cultural journal in North America, as well as all the issues of Lāpa, published by former Fischbach students. Other serial issues relate to academic life in the Latvian emigration (Akadēmiska Dzīve), Latvian military history (Kadets and Latvju Karavīrs), and a Latvian church in San Francisco (Zelta Vārtu Vēstis). There are also two journals published by young Latvian Americans in Sacramento, California (Dzirksts and Sakramento Latvies̆u Jaunatne). In addition, this series contains copies of programs for various Latvian song festivals and theatre productions.
The Organizations file series includes minutes of meetings and other records of the Baltic Alliance of Northern California, a group whose members advocated for the independence of the three Baltic States during the period immediately prior to the collapse of the Soviet Union. The collection also contains a recording of an extensive interview with Pommers in which he describes his own formative experiences, his participation in Latvian-American community life, and recounts some of the political controversies that divided Latvian Americans during the Cold War.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 6 series: Edited works; Writings by others; Organizations file; Printed matter; Sound recording; Photograph
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--Latvia.; Refugees.; Latvians--United States.
Collection Contents
- Edited works, 2004-2010 (Box 1)
  Contains drafts and printed copies of monographs, photographs and reviews, arranged chronologically by title
  - Fis̆bachas virs̆os 1945-1950, 2004-2007 (Folder 1)
    - Draft, 2004 (Folder 1)
      - Paper copy, 2004 (Folder 1: 1)
      - CD-Rom containing digital file, 2004 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Photographs, 2007 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Printed copy, 2007 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Lāpa 15, 2010 (Folder 1)
    - Printed copy, 2010 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Reviews, 2010 (Folder 1: 6)
- Writings by others, 1956-2012 (Box 1-2)
  Contains article, monographs, and research paper, arranged alphabetically by name of author
  - Abula, Biruta (Folder 1)
    - Auseklies̆i no pažobelēm pausaules tālēs 1945-1950, 2004 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Latvies̆u literārie pulciṇi Amerikas Savienotajās Valstīs 1950-2011, 2012 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Anderson, Edgar, "The United States and the Soviet Union in the 1980s," address, San Jose State University, San Jose, California, 1981 April 2 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Ernstons, Arnolds, No Cīravas līds Sanfrancisko, 1996 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Kreismanis, Nicholas, "Latvian Immigrants in the Sacramento Area,", 1956 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Slaidins̆, Raimonds, Latvies̆i Sanfrancisko un tās apkārtnē, 2011 (Folder 2: 4)
- Organizations file, 1952-1998 (Box 2)
  Contains announcements, bumper stickers, financial records, minutes of meetings, and reports, arranged alphabetically by name of organization
  - Baltic Alliance of Northern California, 1990-1998 (Folder 2)
    - Bumper stickers, 1990 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Financial records, 1990-1998 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1990-1993 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Los Gatosas Latviesu Kopa, minutes of meetings, 1952-1953 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Ziemelkalifornijas Latvies̆u Evanġēliski Luteriskā Draudze, report, 1959, 1952-1953 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Zinaīdis Lazda Pieminas Fonds, 1970-1978 (Folder 2)
    - Announcements, 1975-1978 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Report, 1970 (Folder 2: 11)
- Printed matter, 1929-2012 (Box 3-19)
  Contains monograph, pamphlets, programs, and serial issues, arranged by physical form and alphabetically by title thereunder
  - Monograph, Valmieras kājnieku pulka vēsture, 1929 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1975-2003 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Programs for Latvian song festivals and theatre productions, 1946-2008 (Folder 3)
    - 1946-1948 (Folder 3: 3)
    - 1965 (Folder 3: 4)
    - 1972 (Folder 3: 5)
    - 1979 (Folder 3: 6)
    - 2003 (Folder 3: 7)
    - 2006 (Folder 3: 8)
    - 2008 (Folder 3: 9-10)
  - Serial issues, 1955-2012 (Folder 3-19)
    - Akadēmiska Dzīve, 1959-1963 (Folder 3-4)
      - 1959 (Folder 3: 11)
      - 1962 (Folder 3: 12)
      - 1963 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Baltic Bulletin, 2008 September (Folder 4: 2)
    - Brīvība, 1972-1988 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Bulletin of Baltic Studies, 1970 December (Folder 4: 4)
    - Drauga Vēsts, 1945 October/November (Folder 4: 5)
    - Dzirksts, 1960 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Jaunā Gaita, 1955-2012 (Folder 4-10)
      - Nos. 1-2, 1955 (Folder 4: 7)
      - Nos. 3-6, 1956 (Folder 4: 8)
      - Nos. 7-8 and 11-12, 1957 (Folder 4: 9)
      - Nos. 13-18, 1958 (Folder 4: 10)
      - Nos. 19-24, 1959 (Folder 4: 11)
      - Nos. 25-27, 1960 (Folder 4: 12)
      - Nos. 28-33, 1961 (Folder 4: 13)
      - Nos. 34-39, 1962 (Folder 4: 14)
      - Nos. 40-44, 1963 (Folder 4: 15)
      - Nos. 45/46-50, 1964 (Folder 5: 1)
      - Nos. 51-56, 1965 (Folder 5: 2)
      - Nos. 57-60, 1966 (Folder 5: 3)
      - Nos. 61-66, 1967 (Folder 5: 4)
      - Nos. 67-71, 1968 (Folder 5: 5)
      - Nos. 72-76, 1969 (Folder 5: 6)
      - Nos. 77-81, 1970 (Folder 5: 7)
      - Nos. 82 and 84-86, 1971 (Folder 5: 8)
      - Nos. 87-91, 1972 (Folder 6: 1)
      - Nos. 92-96, 1973 (Folder 6: 2)
      - Nos. 97-101, 1974 (Folder 6: 3)
      - Nos. 102-106, 1975 (Folder 6: 4)
      - Nos. 107-111, 1976 (Folder 6: 5)
      - Nos. 112-116, 1977 (Folder 6: 6)
      - Nos. 117-121, 1978 (Folder 6: 7)
      - Nos. 122-126, 1979 (Folder 7: 1)
      - Nos. 127-131, 1980 (Folder 7: 2)
      - Nos. 132-136, 1981 (Folder 7: 3)
      - Nos. 137-141, 1982 (Folder 7: 4)
      - Nos. 142-146, 1983 (Folder 7: 5)
      - Nos. 147-150, 1984 (Folder 7: 6)
      - Nos. 151-155, 1985 (Folder 7: 7)
      - Nos. 156-160, 1986 (Folder 8: 1)
      - Nos. 161-165, 1987 (Folder 8: 2)
      - Nos. 166-170, 1988 (Folder 8: 3)
      - Nos. 171-175, 1989 (Folder 8: 4)
      - Nos. 176-180, 1990 (Folder 8: 5)
      - Nos. 181-185, 1991 (Folder 8: 6)
      - Nos. 186-190, 1992 (Folder 8: 7)
      - Nos. 212-215, 1998 (Folder 9: 1)
      - Nos. 216 and 218-219, 1999 (Folder 9: 2)
      - Nos. 220-223, 2000 (Folder 9: 3)
      - Nos. 224-227, 2001 (Folder 9: 4)
      - Nos. 228-231, 2002 (Folder 9: 5)
      - Nos. 232-235, 2003 (Folder 9: 6)
      - Nos. 236-239, 2004 (Folder 9: 7)
      - Nos. 240-243, 2005 (Folder 9: 8)
      - Nos. 224-245, 2006 (Folder 10: 1)
      - 5 CD-ROMS containing digital files of selected articles from Jaunā Gaita, 1955-2006, and an annotated list of the articles, 2012 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Kadets, 1969-1993 (Folder 10)
      - Nos. 2 and 5-7, 1969-1978 (Folder 10: 3)
      - Nos. 8-11, 1979-1982 (Folder 10: 4)
      - Nos. 12-15, 1983-1987 (Folder 10: 5)
      - Nos. 16-20, 1989-1993 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Laika Griežos, no. 68, 1946 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Lāpa, 1946-1986 (Folder 10-11)
      - Nos. 1-3 and 5-12, 1946-1947 (Folder 10: 8)
      - Bulletins, 1966 (Folder 10: 9)
      - Nos. 4-7 (new series), 1967-1970 (Folder 10: 10)
      - Bulletins, 1970 (Folder 10: 11)
      - Nos. 8-10, 1971-1973 (Folder 10: 12)
      - Nos. 11-12, 1980-1982 (Folder 11: 1)
      - Nos. 13-14, 1983-1986 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Latvian Dimensions, volume 17, no. 1, 2008 (Folder 11: 3)
    - Latvju Karavīrs, 1979-1986 (Folder 11)
      - No. 1, 1979 (Folder 11: 4)
      - No. 2, 1980 (Folder 11: 5)
      - No. 3, 1986 (Folder 11: 6)
    - Sakramento Latvies˨u Jaunatne, 1956-1957 (Folder 11)
      - 1956 (Folder 11: 7)
      - 1957 (Folder 11: 8)
    - Tilts, 1956-1973 (Folder 11)
      - Nos. 17 and 19, 1956-1957 (Folder 11: 9)
      - Nos. 100/101 and 138/139, 1970-1973 (Folder 11: 10)
    - Zelta Vārtu Vēstis, 1954-1979 (Folder 11-12)
      - 1954 January and April/May (Folder 11: 11)
      - 1955 January/February and May (Folder 11: 12)
      - 1956 February and November-December (Folder 11: 13)
      - 1958 May-October (Folder 11: 14)
      - 1961 January/February and October (Folder 11: 15)
      - 1969 November (Folder 11: 16)
      - 1970 April (Folder 11: 17)
      - 1972 January (Folder 11: 18)
      - 1976 February-March and June (Folder 12: 1)
      - 1977 February (Folder 12: 2)
      - 1979 April (Folder 12: 3)
    - Zielmelkalifornijas Apskats, 1959-2010 (Folder 12-19)
      - Annotated list of issues, 2010 (Folder 12: 4)
      - 1959 September-December, 2010 (Folder 12: 5)
      - 1960 January-December, 2010 (Folder 12: 6)
      - 1961 January-December, 2010 (Folder 12: 7)
      - 1962 January/February-December, 2010 (Folder 12: 8)
      - 1963 January-November, 2010 (Folder 12: 9)
      - 1964 January-September and November-December, 2010 (Folder 12: 10)
      - 1965 January and April-December, 2010 (Folder 12: 11)
      - 1966 (Folder 13)
        - January-June (Folder 13: 1)
        - July/August-December (Folder 13: 2)
      - 1967 (Folder 13)
        - January-June (Folder 13: 3)
        - July/August-December (Folder 13: 4)
      - 1968 (Folder 13)
        - January-June (Folder 13: 5)
        - July/August-December (Folder 13: 6)
      - 1969 (Folder 13)
        - January-June (Folder 13: 7)
        - July/August-December (Folder 13: 8)
      - 1970 (Folder 13)
        - January-June (Folder 13: 9)
        - July/August-December (Folder 13: 10)
      - 1971 (Folder 14)
        - January-June (Folder 14: 1)
        - July/August-December (Folder 14: 2)
      - 1972 (Folder 14)
        - January-June (Folder 14: 3)
        - July/August-December (Folder 14: 4)
      - 1973 (Folder 14)
        - January-June (Folder 14: 5)
        - July/August-December (Folder 14: 6)
      - 1974 (Folder 14)
        - January-June (Folder 14: 7)
        - July/August-December (Folder 14: 8)
      - 1975 (Folder 15)
        - January-June (Folder 15: 1)
        - July/August-December (Folder 15: 2)
      - 1976 (Folder 15)
        - January-June (Folder 15: 3)
        - July/August-December (Folder 15: 4)
      - 1977 (Folder 15)
        - January-June (Folder 15: 5)
        - July/August-December (Folder 15: 6)
      - 1978 (Folder 15)
        - January-June (Folder 15: 7)
        - July/August-December (Folder 16: 1)
      - 1979 (Folder 16)
        - January-June (Folder 16: 2)
        - July/August-December (Folder 16: 3)
      - 1980 (Folder 16)
        - January-June (Folder 16: 4)
        - July/August-December (Folder 16: 5)
      - 1981 (Folder 16)
        - January-June (Folder 16: 6)
        - July/August-December (Folder 16: 7)
      - 1982 (Folder 17)
        - January-June (Folder 17: 1)
        - July/August-December (Folder 17: 2)
      - 1983 (Folder 17)
        - January-June (Folder 17: 3)
        - July/August-December (Folder 17: 4)
      - 1984 (Folder 17)
        - January-June (Folder 17: 5)
        - July/August-December (Folder 17: 6)
      - 1985 (Folder 17)
        - January-June (Folder 17: 7)
        - July/August-December (Folder 17: 8)
      - 1986 (Folder 18)
        - January-June (Folder 18: 1)
        - July/August-December (Folder 18: 2)
      - 1987 (Folder 18)
        - January-June (Folder 18: 3)
        - September-December (Folder 18: 4)
      - 1988 (Folder 18)
        - January-June (Folder 18: 5)
        - July/August-December (Folder 18: 6)
      - 1989 (Folder 18)
        - January-June (Folder 18: 7)
        - July/August-December (Folder 18: 8)
      - 1990 (Folder 19)
        - January-June (Folder 19: 1)
        - July/August-December (Folder 19: 2)
      - 1991 (Folder 19)
        - January-June (Folder 19: 3)
        - July/August-December (Folder 19: 4)
      - 1992 (Folder 19)
        - January-June (Folder 19: 5)
        - July/August-December (Folder 19: 6)
      - 1993 March and July/August (Folder 19: 7)
      - 1997 April-May and June/July (Folder 19: 8)
- Sound recording, 2008 (Box 19)
  - Interview of Ansis Pommers by David Jacobs, 2008 July 17 (Folder 19: 9)
    Use copy reference number: 2007c6_a_0001485
    One compact disc containing an interview of Ansis Pommers by David Jacobs, Hoover Institution Archives staff member. Part of the oral history project: The Latvian Emigration in California. In English. Duration 52:33. One compact disc.
- Photograph, 1993 (Box 19)
  Consists of one print
  - One print depicting Ansis Pommers, Maija Ozola, Alissa Ozola, Ojārs Celle, Aivars Savelis, Gunta Golts, and Andrejs Grīslis, on the occasion of voting for 5th Saeima elections, Latvian Hall, San Francisco, California, 1993 (Folder 19: 10)